Register of the James B. Donovan papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Cuban Prisoners Exchange File, 1962-1976 (Boxes 38-60)
  - Mercedarians (Folder 15)
  - Mott, Newcomb (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Narrative by J. Donovan, 1962 October 12 (Folder 2)
  - Negotiating instructions (Folder 3)
  - Negotiations, preparations for (Folder 4)
  - "Newsmakers," WCBS-TV, program transcript, J. B. Donovan, Democratic Candidate for the US Senate, 1962 October 14 (Folder 5)
  - Notes (Folder 6)
  - Playa Giron Invasion
    - Brigade 2506 members, sentence by Cuban Military Tribunal (Folder 7)
    - Indemnification
      - List of products, 1962 September (Folder 8)
      - Memorandum of agreement, 1962 December 21 (Folder 9)
      - Preliminary Report Concerning the Payment of Indemnification for the Invasion of the Playa Giron, 1963 March 16 (Folder 10)
  - Press releases
    - Berquist, Laura, "My 28 Days in Communist Cuba," Look, 1963 April 19 (Folder 11)
    - Chaigne, Herve, "The Cuban Revolution: A Mirror of Our Times," Freres du Monde, No., 3, 1962 (Folder 12)
    - Clayton, James E., Washington Post, 1962 December 25 (Folder 13)
    - "The Cuban Refugee Situation in Dade County," highlights of speech by Marshall Wise, Director of the U.S. Cuban Refugee Center (Folder 14)
    - Drugs in Cuba (Folder 15)
    - Free Cuba News, 1963 May-July (Folder 16)
    - Friedenheim, Milt, Chicago Daily News, n.d. (Folder 17)
    - "The Great Cuban Spy Caper," Maclean's, 1964 February-March (Folder 18)
    - Lindeman, Bard, Saturday Evening Post (Folder 19)
    - Manly, Chesly, articles about J. B. Donovan, Chicago Tribune (Folder 20)
    - Martin, Paul, Rochester Democrat and Chronicle, 1963 January 27 (Folder 21)
    - President's conference in Costa Rica, 1963 March (Folder 22)
    - Senate Hearings on the Fairplay for Cuba Committee, 1963 February 14 (Folder 23)
    - Spanish press on Cuba (Folder 24)
    - "What Can We Do About Cuba? Report of a Freedom House Conference." Speech of Hon. Thomas J. Dodd, Connecticut, in the Senate of the United States, 1963 June 10 (Folder 25)
    - Young, Warren, "Door to Freedom: A Quiet Lawyer's Eloquent Patience," (Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous articles (Folder 27)
  - Prison conditions in Cuba (Folder 28)
  - Prisoner release requests
    - A-Al (Folder 29)
    - Alv-Arn (Folder 30)
    - Aro-Ay (Folder 31)
    - Ba-Ber (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Bet-Boo (Folder 2)
    - Bor-Buz (Folder 3)
    - Cuban political prisoners
      - General (Folder 4)
      - 1964 (Folder 5-6)
      - 1965-1966 (Folder 7-8)
      - 1966 (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
    - Peace Program hostages (Folder 3)
    - Political prisoners in countries other than Cuba (Folder 4)
    - Red China political prisoners (Folder 5)
    - Retainers declined
      - General. Missing persons (Folder 6)
      - A-D (Folder 7)
      - E-K (Folder 8)
      - L-R (Folder 9)
      - S-Z (Folder 10)
    - Unemployed Cubans seeking work (Folder 11)
    - Visa cases (Box 51, Folder 1-2)
  - Prisoners in Cuban prisons
    - Americans (Folder 3)
    - Brigade prisoners released (Folder 4)
    - Geddes, Robert (Folder 5)
    - Gray, Wade (Folder 6)
    - New York Cubans (Folder 7)
    - Schwartz, Abba (Folder 8)
    - Skin divers (Folder 9)
  - Proposal to end Latin America deadlock, head Education Committee, 1963 August-September (Folder 10)
  - Roa, Raul (Folder 11)
  - Robillard, Amos H. (Folder 12)
  - Ryan, John L., activities reports, 1962 July 3-August 24 (Folder 13-14)
  - Sanchez Silveira, Manuel (Folder 15)
  - Skin divers (Folder 16)
  - Spanish language press on Cuba (Folder 17-18)
  - Theatrical presentation requests (Folder 19)
  - Toldi, Isabel (Folder 20)
  - Transportation requests
    - General, 1962 (Box 52, Folder 1-2)
    - Brigade affiliated prisoners (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Brigade members relatives (Folder 2)
    - Cab-Caro (Folder 3)
    - Carr-Con (Folder 4)
    - Cor-Dea (Folder 5)
    - Cuban political prisoners (Folder 6)
    - Dec-Den (Folder 7)
    - Des-Dy (Folder 8)
    - Ec-Ex (Folder 9)
    - Faj-Fern (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Ferr-Gal (Folder 2)
    - Filing and listing system (Folder 3)
    - Form letters (Folder 4)
    - Gar-Gue (Folder 5)
    - Gon-Gue (Folder 6)
    - Gui-Hern (Folder 7)
    - H-K (Folder 8)
    - Herr-Kenn (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Ki-Ly (Folder 2)
    - L-Mar (Folder 3)
    - Mac-Marr (Folder 4)
    - Mart-Maz (Folder 5)
    - McC-Me (Folder 6)
    - Letters returned by Post Office (Folder 7)
    - Lists
      - General (Box 56, Folder 1-2)
      - Multiple (Folder 3)
    - Mas-Mes (Folder 4)
    - Mey-Mon (Folder 5)
    - Mi-Mon (Folder 6)
    - Mo-Mu (Folder 7)
    - Mor-Nu (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Na-On (Folder 2)
    - O-Pez (Folder 3)
    - Or-Paz (Folder 4)
    - Pec-Ph (Folder 5)
    - Pi-Pu (Folder 6)
    - Pi-Raf (Folder 7)
    - Rab-Riv (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Ram-Rob (Folder 2)
    - Roa-Rog (Folder 3)
    - Rodriguez (Folder 4)
    - Roj-Ruz (Folder 5)
    - Rom-Sanzhez (Folder 6)
    - Sa-Sand (Folder 7)
    - Sant-Su (Folder 8)
    - Santa-Som (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - So-Sz (Folder 2)
    - Ta-U (Folder 3)
    - Tam-Vale (Folder 4)
    - Va-Vaz (Folder 5)
    - Vall-Z (Folder 6)
    - Ve-Z (Folder 7)
  - Trips to Cuba
    - 1962 August 29 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - 1962 October 3 (Folder 2)
    - 1962 October 12 (Folder 3)
    - 1962 December 18 (Folder 4)
    - 1962 January 26 (Folder 5)
    - 1962 March 15 (Folder 6)
    - 1963 April 19 (Folder 7)
    - 1963 July 15 (Folder 8)
    - Freyre's notes (Folder 9)
  - Trip to Puerto Rico, 1964 January 21 (Folder 10)
  - Untitled drafts, manuscripts, by J. B. Donovan (Folder 11)
  - Urioste y Mas, Enrique (Folder 12)
  - Valdivia Cordoves, Sergio Ramiro (Folder 13)
  - Voorhess, Douglas (Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 15-16)
- New York City Board of Education File, 1953-1965 (Boxes 61-88)
  Correspondence, memoranda, policy reports and studies, agenda and minutes of meetings, clippings, and other material relating to the operation of schools in New York during J. B. Donovan's term as president, arranged by subject.
  - General
    - General. Letters, memoranda, reports, charts, flyers, pamphlets, newsletters and printed articles primarily relating to the organization of the Board of Education, 1961-1965 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Biographies (Folder 2)
    - Budgets and fiscal matters (Folder 3-5)
    - Budgets and fiscal matters (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1961-1965 (Folder 2-4)
    - Correspondence. Includes memoranda and reports
      - General
        - General. Letters relating to speaking engagements, congratulations, and other letters, most of which relate personally to James Donovan rather than official Board of Education matters (Folder 5-6)
        - General (Box 63, Folder 1-5)
        - 1961-1962 (Folder 6-7)
        - 1963-1965 (Box 64, Folder 1-4)
      - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith. Correspondence, report and newsletter, 1962 (Folder 5)
      - Dulles, Allen. Correspondence, 1964 (Folder 6)
      - Lewis, Edward. Correspondence and a speech transcript, 1963-1964 (Folder 7)
    - Legal materials. Includes memoranda by Robert Morse, Special Counsel to the Board, 1962-1964 (Folder 8-12)
    - Legal materials (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Meeting minutes and agenda
      - 1961 Nov.-1963 Dec. (Folder 2-5)
      - 1964 Jan.-1965 Feb. (Box 66, Folder 1-13)
      - 1965 Feb.-June (Box 67, Folder 1-10)
    - Memoranda
      - General (Folder 11)
      - Board members (Box 68, Folder 1-10)
    - Personnel materials
      - Board of Education, Office of the Secretary. Memoranda and reports, 1961-1965 (Folder 11)
      - Staff
        - General (Folder 12-13)
        - Superintendent
          - General (Folder 14)
          - Gross, Calvin E. (Folder 15)
        - Teachers (Box 69, Folder 1-5)
    - Policy materials. Notebook, by-laws, and memoranda, 1962-1965 (Folder 6-9)
    - Policy materials (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Press releases, 1964-1965 (Folder 2)
    - Reports, Includes supplemental material, 1959-1965. (Folder 3-11)
  - A-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1964-1965 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - Annuities, tax-sheltered. Memoranda, notes and letters, 1963 (Folder 2)
  - B-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 3)
  - Bible reading and prayer. Printed material, letters, and memoranda, 1962-1964 (Folder 4)
  - Board of Examiners. Reports, memoranda, and letters, 1961-1964 (Folder 5-6)
  - Brooklyn schools. Letters, and memoranda, 1962-1965 (Folder 7)
  - C-Miscellaneous. Letters and memoranda, 1958-1965 (Folder 8)
  - Childrens' Bus Service, Inc. Memoranda and contract, 1962 (Folder 9)
  - Civil rights. Printed articles, 1953-1963 (Folder 10)
  - Collective bargaining. Printed material, letters, memoranda, and press releases, 1962-1964 (Box 72, Folder 1-4)
  - Custodial matters. Letters, memoranda and press releases, 1961-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Decentralization. Press releases, clippings, reports, correspondence, and miscellany, 1961-1965 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Donovan, Bernard E. Letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 2)
  - E-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1963-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Educational parks. Letters, memoranda, pamphlet and maps, 1964-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Ethics, Special Committee on. Hearing transcript, 1964 Jan. 22 (Folder 5)
  - Ethnic distributions (New York City and Washington, D.C.). Memoranda and charts, 1964-1965 (Folder 6)
  - F-Miscellaneous. Letters, notes, and pamphlets, 1963-1965 (Folder 7)
  - Federal Aid to Education. Reports, memoranda, letters, and a hearing transcript, 1961-1965 (Folder 8)
  - Five Year Crash Program for Quality Education. Relates to a proposal for the federal government to aid New York City schools. Report, correspondence, press releases, notes, clippings, and memoranda, 1964-1965 (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Foreign languages. Letters, 1964 (Folder 2)
  - G-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1961-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Hodge, David. Letters, printed material and miscellany, 1962-1963 (Folder 4)
  - I-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 5)
  - Integration
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - General. Includes other printed and non-printed material
          - 1963-1964 (Folder 6-7)
          - 1964-1965 (Box 75, Folder 1-3)
        - Letters to black leaders, 1964 January. (Folder 4)
        - White, Theodore H. Correspondence and a printed article, 1963-1964 (Folder 5)
        - Wolff, Max. Letters and memoranda, 1964 (Folder 6)
      - Press releases, 1963-1964 (Folder 7)
      - Printed material. Articles, clippings, and pamphlets, 1963-1965 (Box 76, Folder 1)
      - Reports
        - General. Other organizations (Folder 2-3)
        - New York City Board of Education
          - General. Miscellaneous reports and progress reports, 1962-1965 (Folder 4)
          - "Plan for Integration," Report, drafts, background materials, and memoranda, 1963 Aug. 23. (Box 77, Folder 1)
          - "Memorandum on Integration," Includes memoranda and background material, 1964 Feb. 24. (Folder 2)
          - "Desegregating the Public Schools of New York City," (Allen Committee Report). Includes correspondence, memoranda and miscellany, 1964 May 12. (Folder 3)
          - "Blueprint for Further Action Toward Quality Integrated Education," Includes memoranda, correspondence, press releases, telegrams and miscellany, 1965 March 5. (Folder 4)
          - "Blueprint for Further Action Toward Quality Integrated Education" (Box 78, Folder 1-3)
        - Resolutions and minutes, 1962-1964 (Folder 4)
    - After-school study centers. Letters and memoranda, 1963-1964 (Folder 5-6)
    - Boycotts. Correspondence, memoranda, flyers, petitions, legal materials, attendance statistics, and other miscellany, 1964-1965 (Folder 7-8)
    - Boycotts (Box 79, Folder 1-4)
    - Litigation. Legal materials and memoranda, 1964-1965 (Folder 5)
    - New York City Commission on Human Rights. Report, letters and newsletter, 1963-1965 (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - New York State Department of Education. Pamphlet, press release, and letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 3)
    - Zoning changes. Charts, letters, and reports, 1964 (Folder 4)
  - Investigation Unit. Reports, memoranda, and correspondence, 1962-1964 (Folder 5)
  - J-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1964-1965 (Folder 6)
  - Joint Cooperative Review, New York State and City. Reports, 1962 (Folder 7)
  - Junior high schools. Letters, memoranda, press releases, and reports, 1960-1964 (Folder 8)
  - Junior High School Principals Association. Reports and letter, 1964-1965 (Folder 9)
  - K-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 10)
  - L-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1963-1965 (Folder 11)
  - Labor relations. Minutes, clippings, memoranda, pamphlets, and letters, 1964-1965 (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Large city Boards of Education. Letters and reports, 1964-1965 (Folder 2)
  - Legislation. Memoranda, reports, bulletins, and bills, 1964-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Local school boards. Letters, memoranda, agenda, directory, and reports, 1963-1965 (Folder 4)
  - M-Miscellaneous. Letters and memoranda, 1963-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Maintenance. Letters, memorandum and chart, 1962-1963 (Folder 6)
  - Manhattan schools. Letters, 1963-1965 (Folder 7)
  - Mayor's Office. Memoranda, press release, speech transcript, and report, 1961-1965 (Folder 8)
  - Moral and ethical values. Letters, speech transcript, and press release, 1964-1965 (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - More effective schools. Memorandum and reports, 1965 (Folder 2)
  - Naming of schools. Letters and memoranda, 1962-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Narcotics. Press release and memoranda, 1962 (Folder 4)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). Letters and telegrams, 1965 (Folder 5)
  - New York City, other departments. Correspondence, 1961-1964 (Folder 6)
  - O-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1962-1965 (Folder 7)
  - P-Miscellaneous. Press release, memoranda, letters, and contracts, 1961-1965 (Folder 8)
  - Parent Teachers Association (PTA). Letters, 1961-1963 (Folder 9)
  - Parents and taxpayers. Letters and printed article, 1964-1965 (Folder 10)
  - Playgrounds. Press releases, letters, and newsletter, 1964-1965 (Folder 11)
  - President's Commission on Registration and Voting Participation. Letters, press release, and printed report, 1963 (Folder 12)
  - Principals Association. Letters, report and miscellany, 1963-1964 (Folder 13)
  - Public Education Association. Memoranda, flyers, reports, and newsletter, 1961-1965 (Folder 14)
  - Public relations. Letters, memoranda, pamphlets, newsletters, and clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Puerto Rican students. Letters, press releases, and memoranda, 1963-1964 (Folder 2)
  - Queens schools. Letters, reports, and clippings, 1961-1965 (Folder 3)
  - R-Miscellaneous. Letters, 1961-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Recreation and culture. Clippings, letters, memoranda, reports, and pamphlets, 1961-1964 (Folder 5)
  - Religion. Report, memoranda, press release, letters, and pamphlet, 1964-1965 (Folder 6-7)
  - Richmond schools. Letters and notes, 1961-1965 (Folder 8)
  - S-Miscellaneous. Letter and memoranda, 1963-1965 (Folder 9)
  - School construction
    - General. Memoranda, reports, legal materials, press releases, and letters, 1961-1964 (Box 84, Folder 1-3)
    - Advisory Board. Charts, minutes, and memoranda, 1963-1964 (Folder 4)
    - Investigation materials, 1961-1962 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Site selection. Letters, reports, memoranda, telegrams, printed material and charts, 1962-1965 (Folder 2-4)
    - Contractors. Reports, memoranda, letters, legal materials, and printed material, 1961-1965 (Box 86, Folder 1-2)
  - School lunches. Letters and financial report, 1964-1965 (Folder 3)
  - School planning and research. Memoranda, 1961-1965 (Folder 4)
  - School reorganization. Pamphlet, press releases, memoranda, telegrams, and letters, 1965 (Folder 5)
  - "600" schools. Memoranda, press releases, letter and pamphlet, 1962-1965 (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - State aid. Letters, press releases, reports, budgets, memoranda, pamphlet, speech transcripts, and resolutions, 1962-1965 (Folder 2)
  - State Education Department. Pamphlets, memoranda, letters, press releases, and reports, 1962-1964 (Folder 3)
  - Staten Island Federation of Parent-Teacher Associations. Report, 1964 (Folder 4)
  - Stichman, Herman T. Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Transportation of pupils. Minutes, letters, memoranda, and contract proposals, 1961-1965 (Folder 6)
  - United Federation of Teachers. Letters, memoranda, reports, telegrams, and clippings, 1961-1965 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - United Parents Association. Memoranda, letters, press releases, pamphlets, and newsletters, 1962-1964 (Folder 2)
  - Use of school buildings. Letters, 1961-1963 (Folder 3)
  - Vocational education. Letters, reports, pamphlets, and memoranda, 1961-1965 (Folder 4)
  - World's Fair, 1964. Memoranda, letters, speech transcripts, report, and printed articles relating to a proposal to use the buildings for an educational park, 1964-1965 (Folder 5)
- Restricted File, 1962-1963
  - Closed. Original copies of material on the Cuban prisoner exchange which were removed from boxes 39 (folders 1-11) and 40 (folders 1-5) and replaced with photocopies (Boxes 89-90)
- Oversize File, 1944-1967 (Boxes 91-97)
  Scrapbooks, clippings, serial issue, card files, and book illustration drawings and plates.
  - Chart and two scrapbooks relating to the Nuremberg trials; one scrapbook relating to the Office of Strategic Services (Box 91)
  - Two scrapbooks of clippings and other material relating to the Abel case (Box 92)
  - Three scrapbooks of clippings and other material relating to the Abel case (Box 93)
  - One scrapbook of clippings relating to the Mr. Donovan's Senatorial campaign, 1962 (Box 94)
  - One scrapbook relating to Cuban prisoners; clippings relating to the defection of Major Richard Pearce to Cuba; card files relating to Cuban prisoners (Box 95)
  - Two scrapbooks relating to Cuban prisoners; 14 drawings, some of which appear to have been used as illustrations in Strangers on a Bridge, as well as cover design illustration materials; issue of Esquire magazine, relating to spying and the U-2 incident; and miscellaneous clippings, 1966 May (Box 96)
  - Two scrapbooks relating to the New York City Board of Education (Box 97)
- Photographs, 1945-1962
  - 25 prints depicting exhibit materials used in the US vs. Abel trials, 1957-1959 (Envelope A)
  - 2 prints of Francis Gary Powers, undated (Box 91, Envelope B)
  - 3 prints of James B. Donovan and other officials at the International Military Tribunal, Nuremberg, war crimes trials, 1945 (Envelope C)
  - 18 prints of J. B. Donovan, Fidel Castro, and other individuals in Cuba, undated (Envelope D)
  - 9 prints of J. B. Donovan during various stages of his life with associates and family members, undated (Envelope E)
  - 17 prints of J. B. Donovan on a walking tour of Manhattan College and advance taping of "Race for the Senate," WNEW-TV, New York, 1962 November (Envelope F)
  - 6 prints of J. B. Donovan and other during the taping of "Newmakers," WCBS-TV, New York, 1962 October 14 (Envelope G)
  - 2 prints of J. B. Donovan with President Kennedy, Senator Jacob Javits, and John Tillman, undated (Envelope H)
  - 55 prints of J. B. Donovan on a walking tour in Brooklyn, the Bronx, Manhattan, and Staten Island, 1962 October/November (Envelope I)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1944-1945 (Reading room Workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Available as PDF files. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - Records released in 2010, 1944-1945